Guide to the Herbarium Photographs 1904-1963
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
Herbarium Photographs
1904-1963
1904-1920
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
P 093
Oregon State University. Herbarium.
0.25 cubic ft. ca. 80 items
The Herbarium Photographs were made or assembled by curators of the Herbarium and students in the Department of Botany and Plant Pathology. The images depict a variety of subjects including Pacific Northwest species of plants and trees, the Oregon Agricultural College greenhouses, botany research and teaching, and logging operations.
Historical Note:
Since its establishment in the early 1880s, the Herbarium has served as the chief repository for the University's collection of flora as well as a laboratory for the study and identification of plants and fungi. Managed since 1883 by a Curator under the auspices of the Department of Botany and Horticulture, the focus of the Herbarium has shifted away from the traditional role of student instruction and more toward the acquisition and cataloging of Pacific Northwest plant specimens. As a research facility, the Herbarium has become the leading center for research on the taxonomy of mycorrhizal fungi. Currently housed at Cordley Hall, the Herbarium has moved many times from its original location in Education Hall. The Herbarium has also resided in the Strand Agricultural building, the basement of the Memorial Union, and Gill Coliseum. In 1993, under pressure to cut costs stemming from state budget reductions, the University of Oregon Herbarium merged with the facility at OSU, increasing the number of plant specimens housed at Cordley Hall by nearly one- third. Willamette University's collection of flora has also recently been transferred to the OSU Herbarium.
This collection consists of photographs from the Herbarium. About half of the photographs are identified and one-third are dated. The images depict a variety of plants and trees both in the wild and in greenhouses, famous botanists, Curators of the Herbarium including E.R. Lake and Helen Gilkey, botany students engaged in research in the classroom and in the field, logging operations, and views of Marys Peak taken from several locations.
There are 29 prints in this collection: 28 b/w and 1 color. The remainder of the photographic images are nitrate and glass plate negatives with no prints.
The photographs are numbered P093:01-P093:69.
In addition to the photographs of the Herbarium, other materials relating to OSU's role in plant instruction and research include: the records of the Herbarium (RG 117), the records and photographs of the Botany and Plant Pathology Department (RG 54, P 75), the records and photographs of the Horticulture Department (RG 187, P 90), and the records of the OSU Horticultural Society (RG 151). The personal papers of Helen Gilkey, who served as the Curator of the Herbarium from 1918 to 1951, also contain materials pertaining to the Herbarium, including an unpublished manuscript of the history of the facility.
Gilkey, Helen Margaret, 1886-; Lake, E. R. (Edward Ralph), b. 1860.; Lawrence, William E. (William Evans), 1883-1947.
Oregon Agricultural College. Dept. of Botany and Plant Pathology.; Oregon Agricultural College--Buildings.
Botany--Study and teaching--Oregon--Corvallis.; Botany--Oregon.; Greenhouses--Oregon--Corvallis.; Lumber trade--Oregon.; Logging railroads--Oregon.; Women botanists--Oregon--Benton County.; Botanists.
Marys Peak (Or.)
Photographic prints.; Nitrate negatives.; Glass negatives.
Oregon; Photographs; Logging; Colleges and Universities; Science; Women
- Showing characteristic habitat of Riccia Natans at the Oregon Electric Railway Bridge, Beach's Woods, October 29, 1914; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:01 (Box 1)
- "Umpqua Valley looking southeast showing prune orchard, and corn field to the right of the river. On the north side may be seen the extent of a stream as shown by the line of firs bordered by a zone of oaks."; Near Kellogg, Oregon, July 27, 1918; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:02 (Box 1)
- Silver Lake, ca. 1920; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:03 (Box 1)
- Bed of Silver Lake, 1919; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:04 (Box 1)
- A "shoe string" ranch, Hinton Creek Valley; east of Heppner, June 30, 1919; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:05 (Box 1)
- Head of sheep grazing in Brock Meadows, Wenaha National Forest, August 1, 1916; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:06; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Logging dumping pool and tracks, 1910; P093:07; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Abris Nobilis, chiefly felled for logging, 1910; P093:08; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Logging train backing down to dumping pool, 1910; P093:09; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Abris Nobilis, chiefly felled for logging, 1910; P093:10; 3 prints (Box 1)
  Different from P093:08.
- Logging mill and train trestle, ca. 1910; P093:11; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Standing timber before logging, 1910; P093:12; 3 prints (Box 1)
- "Spruce log on flat car, with A.A. Asbahr County Agent of Lincoln County and Harry N. Bowler, Seims Carey H.S., Kerbaugh Corp. Seattle. Log 8 ft in diameter and 304 years old, Toledo, Oregon", 1918; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:13 (Box 1)
- Looking up Crooked River Canyon, ca. 1920; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:14 (Box 1)
- Botany class, ca. 1904; P093:15; 8x10 glass plate negative (Box 2)
- Mt. Chintimini, Marys Peak, taken from OAC barns, 1915; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:16; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Mt. Chintimini, Marys Peak, taken from OAC barns, 1915; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:17 (Box 1)
- Marys Peak from Tinker's Hill, 1917; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:18 (Box 1)
- Marys Peak from Forestry Building, OAC, 1917; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:19; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Marys Peak, 1917; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:20; 2 prints (Box 1)
- Marys Peak from Tinker's Hill, 1917; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:21 (Box 1)
- Greenhouses; interior, 1903-1924; P093:23-P093:29; 8x10 glass negatives (Box 3)
- Zuercus Garryanna(height 49 ft), SW of OAC, ca. 1910; P093:30 (Box 1)
- Armory Building (McAlexander Fieldhouse) on OAC campus at Armory and Jefferson St., ca. 1910; P093:31; 3 prints (Box 1)
- "Class in forest botany identifying woody plants in their winter condition in Beeche's Woods, east of the Willamette. Pictured, left to right: S.E. Brett, Lundeen, Benjamin Culver, and LeRoy Wooks", 1914; Photo by William Lawrence.; P093:32; 3 prints (Box 1)
- Mass of Sisymbrium Officinale growing along roadside near Alpha Hall on 22nd St., Corvallis, 1914; Photo by V. Walls.; P093:33 (Box 1)
- undated, P093:34-P093:52; copy negatives on nitrate film stock
  P093:34-P093:40 are identified and appear to have been copied from a publication on famous botanists. Images P093:41-P093:52 are unidentified.
  - Millardet, Alexis, P093:34 (Box 4)
  - Douglas, David, P093:35 (Box 4)
  - Von Linne, Carl, P093:36 (Box 4)
  - Gray, Asa, P093:37 (Box 4)
  - Atkinson, George F., P093:38 (Box 4)
  - Kuhn, Julius, P093:39 (Box 4)
  - De Bary, Anton, P093:40 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified Botanists, P093:41-P093:52 (Box 4)
- Fuschia, ca. 1904; Photo by Earl Beaconsfield.; P093:53; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Art class, ca. 1904; P093:54; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Military cadets at inspection, ca. 1904; P093:55-P093:57; 8x10 glass negatives (Box 3)
- Botany class, ca. 1904; P093:58; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Benton Hall, ca. 1904; P093:59; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Mechanical drawing class, ca. 1904; P093:60; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Palm tree; decorative, ca. 1905; P093:61; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Botany students, ca. 1904; P093:62; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Plants, ca. 1904; P093:63; 8x10 glass negative (Box 3)
- Greenhouse; interior, ca. 1904; P093:64-P093:65; 8x10 glass negatives (Box 3)
- "Professor E.R. Lake, Head of Botany and Horticulture when Oregon State became a land grant college. Helen Gilkey and Lillie Riggs-Kinney are also in the photo", ca. 1946; P093:66 (Box 1)
- Professor E.R. Lake, ca. 1946; P093:67 (Box 1)
- "Professor E.R. Lake, when he visited in Corvallis about ca. 1950". Our yard.", P093:68; Color photo (Box 1)
- Pereskia Aculeata. (Photo attached to a letter from F. McWhorter to Dr. P.C. Hutchison, October 1, 1963; P093:69 (Box 1)